Register of the Pierre Lanneret Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Pierre Lanneret papers,
1902-1994
93032
Lanneret, Pierre, 1921-1993
17 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (7.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, notes, correspondence, serial issues, pamphlets, leaflets, internal bulletins, and photographs, relating to left-wing resistance activities in France during World War II, and to libertarian socialist and communist movements in France, the United States and elsewhere.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1921 Born, Auxerre, France
1938 Becomes employed as a typesetter Joins La Jeunesse Revolutionnaire Socialiste, a Trotskyist group
1942-1943 Sent to Germany as a laborer under the terms of la Service du Travail Obligatoire
1943 Joins the Groupe Révolutionnaire Prolétarien, a clandestine group of "revolutionary internationalists," in Paris
1946-1950 Active in the Bordigist group, la Fraction Française de la Gauche Communiste
1950 Joins Socialisme ou Barbarie
1951 Emigrates to Canada
1958 Moves to San Francisco, becoming member of the Typographical Union
1970-1975 Member, International Socialists
1976-1979 Member, A World to Win
1985 Third Camp Internationalists in France during World War II
1993 Dies
Scope and Content Note
Acquired in 1987, with a significant increment received in 2001, the Pierre Lanneret papers in the Hoover Institution Archives provide a window on the history of 20th century French working-class radicalism, and in particular, on the life of small but influential groups whose politics were situated well to the left of the French Communist Party. It also documents the activities of similar groups in the United States and the United Kingdom.
Having entered the labor force as an adolescent in France, Lanneret worked in the printing trades as a typesetter and composer until his retirement in 1984. At the same time, he devoted a life's work and intellectual effort to revolutionary politics, participating as a militant in several organizations, and conducting an extensive correspondence with a number of like-minded individuals, a connection which in many cases endured long after any period of formal organizational collaboration.
Lanneret's first political engagement was with a Trotskyist youth group in his native Auxerre, but by the time of the Second World War, his views had shifted in the direction of a revolutionary internationalist perspective, which did not view the Soviet Union as socialist, and which opposed both Nazi Germany and the Allied powers, seeing the war as the expression of imperialist rivalries, not as an anti-fascist crusade.
At considerable personal risk, Lanneret evaded obligatory labor service in Germany during the Nazi occupation of France and went underground in Paris, joining a small resistance group, the Groupe Révolutionnaire Prolétarien, which also espoused a "third camp internationalist" perspective. This clandestine group engaged in limited propaganda work and some direct action. Its history, along with that of other similar groups, is described in Lanneret's work, Third Camp Internationalists in France during World War II, various editions of which are found in the collection, along with extensive research materials consulted in the preparation of this monograph (see SPEECHES AND WRITINGS series). A German translation of the joint autobiography of Paul (Pavel) and Clara Thalman, which also discusses the activities of the Groupe Révolutionnaire Prolétarien, is included in the WRITINGS BY OTHERS series in the collection.
After the war, Lanneret was an early member of the group Socialisme ou Barbarie, whose ideas on modern revolution and the nature of bureaucracy were later to exert a considerable influence on the anti-authoritarian currents of the student and worker revolt in France during May-June 1968. Although he emigrated to North America, living first in Canada and then in San Francisco, Lanneret continued to meet and correspond with his former associates in the French revolutionary milieu.
Among these was the philosopher Cornelius Castoriadis, the principal theorist of Socialisme ou Barbarie. The collection contains Castoriadis's correspondence with Lanneret, translations made by Lanneret of some of Castoriadis's writings, and an extensive selection of those writings in the original French (See TRANSLATIONS and WRITINGS BY OTHERS series). There are also copies of the review, Socialisme ou barbarie, in which can be found articles by Castoriadis, Claude Lefort, and others (see PRINTED MATTER series).
The PRINTED MATTER series in the collection also contains a number of rare or fugitive pamphlets and serial issues from political groups in France, the United States, and the United Kingdom. There are extensive materials from the British Solidarity group, which was highly influenced by Socialisme ou Barbarie, and from the French councilist group Informations Correspondance Ouvrières, an offshoot of Socialisme ou Barbarie. In addition, there is a considerable number of publications from fairly obscure leftist groups in the United States in the 1930s, and from Trotskyist and Maoist groups in France in the post-1968 period. There is a considerable amount of publications from groups identified with the Bordigist tendency in revolutionary Marxist politics.
The collection also contains some serial issues relating specifically to the May-June 1968 events in France (see OVERSIZE MATERIALS), and recordings of songs associated with the Paris Commune, 1871.
A feature of the political movements in which Lanneret was involved was the common use of pseudonyms, both as a practice imposed by conditions of wartime clandestinity and as a habit continued afterward. Where appropriate, these pseudonyms have been given in the case of deceased individuals to aid in the identification of writings and correspondence.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Fourth International.; Anarchism--France.; Communism.; Communism--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; World War, 1939-1945--France.; World War, 1939-1945.; Socialism--United States.; Socialism--France.; French--United States.; Communism--France.; United States--Politics and government.; France.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1993-1994. (Box 1)
  Biographies and inventory, arranged by physical form
- Correspondence, 1969-1992. (Box 1)
  Letters and enclosures, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1977-2003. (Box 2-3)
  Article, lecture, monograph, notes, outlines, research materials, and translations, arranged chronologically
- Translations, 1974-1982. (Box 3)
  Translations of articles by Cornelius Castoriadis, arranged chronologically
- Notebooks, 1930s-1950s. (Box 3)
  Notebooks, arranged alphabetically by major theme
- World to Win File, 1976-1979. (Box 4)
  Correspondence, internal documents and position papers, notebook, and publication, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1927-2002. (Box 4-5)
  Clippings, monographs, obituaries, pamphlets, and serial issues, largely relating to revolutionary movements and individuals, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Writings by Others, 1950-1982. (Box 5-7)
  Articles, pamphlets, and papers, arranged alphabetically by author
- Printed Matter, 1936-1995. (Box 8-17)
  Pamphlets and serial issues, arranged by physical form and therein alphabetically by name of organization or title
- Oversize Materials, 1902-1984. (Box 18)
  Phonotapes, photographs, poster, and serial issues, arranged alphabetically by physical form
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1993-1994 (Folder 1)
  - Biographies
    - "Pierre Lanneret: Biographical Details," n.d. (Folder 1: 1)
      Holograph notes
    - Cohen, Larry, "Pierre Remembered," 1993. (Folder 1: 2)
      Typescript
    - Simon, Henri, "Pierre Lanneret, alias Camille," 1994. (Folder 1: 3)
      Typescript. Includes accompanying letter, 1994 May 5
  - Inventory of serial issues in personal library, n.d. (Folder 1: 4)
    Holograph
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1969-1992
  - Unidentified, 1976. (Folder 1: 5)
    Letter from Margaret, with reference to Maximilien Rubel
  - Alexander, Robert J., 1991-1992 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius, 1975-1991 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Cohen, Larry, n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
  - Davoust, Gaston (pseudonym, Henri Chazé), 1969-1984 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Goldner, Loren, 1987-1988 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Gontarbert, Sania, n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - Jacobs, David, 1987-1992 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Klein, Stephanie, 1989-1981 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Lefievre, M., 1983 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Martine, J., 1989-1991 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Rubel, Maximilien, 1969-1991 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Thalman, Clara, 1980-1986 (Folder 1: 17)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1977-2003 (Box 2)
  - Comments on La revolución en cuestión(es), n.d. (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Marx and the State," lecture, n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
  - Notes on France, n.d. (Folder 2: 3)
  - Notes on Hegel and Marx, n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
  - Notes on the history of revolutionary movements in France, n.d. (Folder 2: 5)
  - Notes on the Russian Revolution, n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Notes on The GPU in the Trotskyist Movement by Georges Vereeken," n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
  - Writings on "the national question," n.d.
    - Clippings, pamphlets, and other research materials (Folder 2: 8)
    - Holograph notes (Folder 2: 9)
    - Lecture outlines. (Folder 2: 10)
      Holograph and typescript
  - "The Basque Question," lecture outline, 1977. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Problèmes du syndicalisme dans le Livre en Amérique du Nord," Tribune libre, 1984(?). (Folder 2: 12)
    Printed copy
  - Response to "Appel pour une Union mondiale des tendances révolutionnaires," 1984 February. (Folder 2: 13)
    Printed copy of brochure, with Lanneret's text attributed to "P.L."
  - "Nicaragua: Quelques impressions de voyage," 1986 November. (Folder 2: 14)
  - Third Camp Internationalists in France during World War II, 1987.
    Originally published under the pseudonym Ernest Rayner
    - Research materials, arranged by organization
      - General. Bibliographies, clippings, and pamphlets, 1939-1987 (Folder 2: 15)
      - Centre International de Recherches sur l'Anarchisme. Les Anarchistes et la Résistance, volumes 1 and 2, 1984-1985. (Folder 2: 16)
      - Comité Exécutif Européen de la IVe Internationale. IVe Internationale, no. 4, 1944 February. (Folder 2: 17)
      - Groupe Révolutionnaire Prolétarien. Le Réveil prolétarien, nos. 2, 3, 15, and two unnumbered issues, 1943-1945. (Folder 2: 18)
        Printed copies. Also includes printed copy of manifesto, "Le Groupe Révolutionnaire: Aux travailleurs, aux exploités, aux révolutionnaires," 1943
      - Parti Communiste Internationaliste. La lutte des trotskystes sous la terreur nazie, 1945. (Box-folder 3: 1)
      - Parti Ouvrier Internationaliste. La Vérité, nos. 44 and 50 (supplement), 1943. (Folder 3: 2)
        Printed copies
      - Revolutionären Kommunisten Deutschlands. Spartakus, no. 1, 1943 May 1. (Folder 3: 3)
      - Union Communiste. Printed copies of two leaflets, 1935-1936, and typescript of an internal bulletin, 1935 December (Folder 3: 4)
      - Union des Communistes Internationalistes. La Flamme, nos. 1-2, 1946. (Folder 3: 5)
        Also includes printed copy of leaflet, 1944 October
    - Holograph notes (Folder 3: 6)
    - Proofs (Folder 3: 7)
    - Printed copy (Folder 3: 8)
    - Abridged version published in Échanges, no. 74/75, 1994. (Folder 3: 9)
      Also includes obituary of Lanneret. Printed copy
    - Second edition, Phoenix Press, London, 1995. (Folder 3: 10)
      Includes biography of Lanneret. Photocopy
    - French translation (incomplete), n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
    - Italian translation, Gli internazionalisti del terzo fronte. (Folder 3: 12)
      Printout from internet resource, 2003
  - Notes on China, 1989. (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Notes sur le Guatemala," 1990. (Folder 3: 14)
- TRANSLATIONS, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius
    - "Proletariat and Organization," 1974(?). Translation of "Prolétariat et organization," Socialisme ou barbarie, nos. 27-28, 1959. (Folder 3: 15)
    - "The Power at the End of the Tank," 1982. Translation of an interview with Castoriadis, Nouvel observateur, 1982 January 2. (Folder 3: 16)
- NOTEBOOKS, 1930s-1950s
  - Marx and Engels, 1930s (Folder 3: 17)
  - Political economy, 1930s (Folder 3: 18)
  - Proudhon, 1930s (Folder 3: 19)
  - Russian Revolution, 1930s (Folder 3: 20)
  - Trotsky, 1930s (Folder 3: 21)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950s (Folder 3: 22)
- WORLD TO WIN FILE, 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence.
    Does not include letters either to or from Lanneret
    - 1976-1977 (Folder 4: 1)
    - 1978-1979 (Folder 4: 2)
  - Internal documents and position papers, 1976 (Folder 4: 3-4)
  - Notebook, 1977 (Folder 4: 5)
  - Publication. Now and After, nos. 1-3, 1977-1978. (Folder 4: 6)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1927-2002
  - Anarchism, 1970-1989. (Folder 4: 7)
    Includes printed copy of an article by Noam Chomsky
  - Bordiga, Amadeo, 1932-1987. (Folder 4: 8)
    Includes notes by Lanneret on Bordiga and his followers
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius, 1997. (Folder 4: 9)
    Printed copies of three obituaries
  - China-History, 1949-1989, 1960-1969. (Folder 4: 10)
    Includes articles from Socialisme ou barbarie on China and Maoism
  - Colombia-Social conditions, 1982 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Communism, 1970-1990 (Folder 4: 12)
  - Davoust, Gaston (pseudonym, Henri Chazé), 1984. (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Printed copies of two obituaries
  - Draper, Hal, 1990. (Folder 5: 2)
    Includes typescript of obituary
  - Eastern Europe, 1989. (Folder 5: 3)
    Includes general analyses of perestroika era
  - Education-France, 1989. (Folder 5: 4)
    Printed copies of articles relating to the status of lay education in France
  - Faucier, Nicolas, 1992. (Folder 5: 5)
  - Giraud, Marius, n.d. (Folder 5: 6)
    Printed copy of obituary
  - Guilloré, Raymond, 1989. (Folder 5: 7)
  - Humanist Party (California), 1989 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Lefeuvre, René, 1988. (Folder 5: 9)
  - Maitron, Jean, 1993 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Martinet, Marcel, 1989 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Marxism, 1948-1992. (Folder 5: 12)
    Includes reviews of the works of the Marx scholar, Maximilien Rubel
  - Masó, Albert (pseudonym, Albert Vega), 2002. (Folder 5: 13)
  - Miasnikov, G. T, 1984 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Montseny, Frederica, 1989 (Folder 5: 15)
  - Nicaragua-History, 1979-, 1986 (Folder 5: 16)
  - Pacifism, 1985 (Folder 5: 17)
  - Persian Gulf War, 1991, 1991 (Folder 5: 18)
  - Portugal-Revolution, 1975, 1975 (Folder 5: 19)
  - Saulière, Jean (pseudonym, André Arru), 1995 (Folder 5: 20)
  - Soviet Union-History, 1917-1991, 1989-1990 (Folder 5: 21)
  - Trade unions
    - France, 1974-1976. (Folder 5: 22)
      Includes clipping relating to the Lip strike and occupation, Besançon, 1974
    - Spain, 1986 (Folder 5: 23)
  - Trotsky, Leon, 1927-1991 (Folder 5: 24)
  - Valière, Marcel, 1975. (Folder 5: 25)
    Printed copy of biographical pamphlet
  - Willis, Lillian, 1989. (Folder 5: 26)
  - Workers Revolutionary Party, n.d. (Folder 5: 27)
- WRITINGS BY OTHERS, 1950-1982
  - Brendel, Cajo, 1975-1981 (Folder 5: 28)
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius (pseudonyms, Paul Cardan, Pierre Chaulieu), 1950-1958 (Folder 5: 29-30)
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius, 1961-1998 (Box-folder 6: 1-5)
  - Davoust, Gaston (pseudonym, Henri Chazé), 1978 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Glaberman, Martin, 1969 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Goldner, Loren, 1977-1990 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Gontarbert, Sania, 1989 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Jacobs, David, 1975-1991 (Folder 6: 10)
  - Korsch, Karl, 1971 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Martine, J., 1989 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Rothbart, Ron, 1975-1981 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Rubel, Maximilien, 1951-1991 (Folder 7: 4-7)
  - Seidman, Michael, n.d. (Folder 7: 8)
  - Simon, Henri, 1977 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Thalman, Paul (Pavel) and Clara, 1977 (Folder 7: 10-11)
  - Zerzan, John, 1975 (Folder 7: 12)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1936-1995 (Box 8)
  - Pamphlets, arranged by issuing organization
    - Courant Communiste International (International Communist Current)
      - In English, 1975-1976 (Folder 8: 1)
      - In French, 1988. (Folder 8: 2-3)
        Includes a history of the Bordigist movement in Italy, France, and Belgium
    - Échanges et Mouvement, 1975-1978 (Folder 8: 4)
    - International Socialists (United States), n.d. (Folder 8: 5)
    - Leninist League, U.S.A., n.d. (Folder 8: 6)
    - News and Letters, 1976 (Folder 8: 7)
    - Programme Communiste, 1972 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Revolutionary Workers League, 1938-1948 (Folder 8: 9)
    - Revolutionary Workers Party, n.d. (Folder 8: 10)
    - Solidarity (United Kingdom)
      - Undated (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
      - 1970-1977 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Solidarity (United States), 1974 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Union des Travailleurs Communistes, 1975 (Folder 9: 6)
  - Serial issues, arranged by title
    - A: Rivista anarchica, vol. 8, nos. 9-10, 1978-1979 (Folder 9: 7)
    - À Contre-courant, no. 0, 1988 February (Folder 9: 8)
    - Alarme, no. 39, 1988 January-March (Folder 9: 9)
    - The Bulletin.
      Published by the Workers League for a Revolutionary Party, identified with the political tendency of George Marlen
      - 1941 June-1943 December (Folder 9: 10)
      - 1944 May - 1949 May-June (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Cause du peuple, 1971-1975 (Folder 10: 2)
    - Class Struggle.
      Published by the Communist League of Struggle (Internationalist-Communist), identified with the political tendency of Albert Weisbord
      - 1934 November-1936 December (Folder 10: 3)
      - 1937 March-September (Folder 10: 4)
    - Communist Program, no. 66, nos. 1-3 (new series), 1975-1977. (Folder 10: 5)
      Published by the International Communist Party
    - Connexions, no. 5, 1982 summer (Folder 10: 6)
    - Critique, no. 1, 1973 spring (Folder 10: 7)
    - Échanges, nos. 11, 25, 58, 59, 76/77, 78/79, 1981-1995. (Box-folder 11: 1)
      Published by Échanges et mouvement
    - The Fighting Worker, 1937 March 20-1940 January 15. (Folder 11: 2)
      Published by the Revolutionary Workers League
    - Fourth International, volume 3, no. 10, 1938 June. (Folder 11: 3)
    - Front rouge, nos. 101, 103, 107, 110, 122, 124, 135, 139, 166, 1974 January 31-1975 September 15. (Folder 11: 4)
      Published by the Parti Communiste Révolutionnaire (marxiste-léniniste)
    - L'Humanité rouge, nos. 207-208, 211, 213, 215-216, 221, 225, 238, 1973 November 29-1974 July 24 (Folder 11: 5)
    - In Defense of Bolshevism, volume 1, nos. 5 and 8, volume 2, nos. 1-2, 1938 May-1939 February-March. (Folder 11: 6)
      Published by the Leninist League, U.S.A.
    - Informations correspondance ouvrières (Box 12)
      - Nos. 42, 71 (supplement), 72 (supplement), 85-90, 93-94, 97/98-99, 1965-1970 (Folder 12: 1)
      - Nos. 103/104-112/113, 1971-1972 (Folder 12: 2)
      - Nos. 114-123, 1972-1973 (Folder 12: 3)
    - International Bulletin, nos. 6 and 8, 1948-1949. (Folder 12: 4)
      Published by American Fraction, Left Communist International
    - International News, 1939 September-1945 November. (Folder 12: 5)
    - International Review.
      Published by the International Communist Current
      - Nos. 5, 7, 12-16, 1976-1979 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Nos. 17-25, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 13: 1)
      - Nos. 26-31, 1981-1982 (Folder 13: 2)
    - Internationalism.
      Published by the American affiliate of the International Communist Current
      - Nos. 2, 4-5, 7, 9, 14, 1973-1978 (Folder 13: 3)
      - Nos. 15, 18-27, 38, 54, 62, 1978-1989 (Folder 13: 4)
    - L'Internationaliste, 1947 November. (Folder 13: 5)
      Published by the Fraction Française de la Gauche Communiste Internationale
    - Labor Front, volume 3, nos. 4-5, 1936 September-November. (Folder 13: 6)
      Published by the League for a Revolutionary Workers Party
    - Lutte communiste, 1975 October 24. (Folder 13: 7)
      Published by the Parti Communiste Révolutionnaire (Trotskiste)
    - The Marxist, 1939 April-August. (Folder 13: 8)
    - New International Bulletin, vol. 1, no. 5, 1936 December; vol. 2, no. 1, 1937 March. (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - News and Letters, vol. 24, no. 10, 1979 December; vol. 28, no. 8, 1983 October (Folder 14: 2)
    - Problems of Communism
      - 1967 September/October-November/December (Folder 14: 3)
      - 1972 November/December (Folder 14: 4)
    - Programma communista, 1977 April 8–1978 April 29. (Folder 14: 5)
      Published by the Italian section of the Partito comunista internationale
    - Prolétaire, miscellaneous issues, 1971-1975. (Folder 14: 6)
      Published by the Parti communiste international
    - Quotidien du peuple, 1975 September 30 (Folder 14: 7)
    - Revolt.
      - Volume 1, nos. 2, 4-5, 7, 10-13, 1938 (Folder 14: 8)
      - Volume 2, nos. 2-6, 8-10, 17-18, 1939; volume 3, no. 1, 1940 (Folder 14: 9)
    - Socialisme ou barbarie (Box 15)
      - Nos. 11, 18, 21, 1952-1957 (Folder 15: 1)
      - Nos. 22, 23, 1957-1958 (Folder 15: 2)
      - Nos. 25, 26, 1958 (Folder 15: 3)
      - Nos. 29, 31-32, 1959-1961 (Folder 15: 4)
      - Nos. 33-35, 1961-1964 (Folder 15: 5)
      - Nos. 36-38, 1964 (Box-folder 16: 1)
      - Nos. 39-40, 1965 (Folder 16: 2)
    - Solidarity, no. 2, 1976; no. 9, 1985. (Folder 16: 3)
      Published by the Solidarity group, United Kingdom
    - Solidarity for Social Revolution, nos. 1-10, and 15, 1978-1981. (Folder 16: 4)
    - Solidarity for Workers' Power, vol. 7, nos. 8 and 12, 1973-1974; vol. 8, nos. 1-4 and 7, 1975-1977. (Folder 16: 5)
    - Solidarity Motor Bulletin, nos. 1-8, 1973-1978. (Folder 16: 6)
    - Textures
      - No. 7/8, 1970; no. 1, 1971 (Folder 16: 7)
      - No. 6/7, 1973; no. 10/11, 1975 (Folder 16: 8)
    - Tout le pouvoir aux travailleurs, nos. 00, 2, 5, 13, 16, 18, 21, 25-26, 30, 34, 1976-1980. (Box-folder 17: 1)
      Published by the Union des Travailleurs Communistes Libertaires
    - Workers' Voice, vol. 4, nos. 3 and 8, 1937. (Folder 17: 2)
      Published by the League for a Revolutionary Workers' Party
    - World Revolution.
      Published by the British affiliate of the International Communist Current
      - Nos. 1-2, 7, 17-22, 1974-1979 (Folder 17: 3)
      - Nos. 23-33, 1979-1980 (Folder 17: 4)
      - Nos. 35-54, 1981-1982 (Folder 17: 5)
    - Young Worker, vol. 1, no. 2, 1939 April. (Folder 17: 6)
      Published by the Young Workers League, youth organization of the Revolutionary Workers League
    - Zerowork, no. 2, 1977 fall (Folder 17: 7)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1902-1984 (Box 18)
  - Phonotapes, n.d.
    Sound recordings of songs associated with the Paris Commune, 1871
    - One compact audio cassette containing the recording, "Les Quatre Barbus chantent la Commune de Paris" (Folder 18: 1)
    - One compact audio cassette containing the recording, "Marc Ogeret chante autour de la Commune, 1846-1888" (Folder 18: 2)
  - Photographs
    - One print depicting Harry Bridges on a picket line, San Francisco, n.d. (Folder 18: 3)
    - Two prints depicting Pavel Thalman, and one print depicting Pavel and Clara Thalman, n.d. (Folder 18: 4)
    - One framed print depicting Maximilien Rubel, n.d. (Folder 18: 5)
    - Three prints depicting Pierre Lanneret at a party in honor of his retirement from the San Francisco Newspaper Co., 1984 (Folder 18: 6)